let's find a closed formula for the sum
of triangular
numbers the M triangular number T subm
is the sum of the first M positive
integers this number can be represented
by a triangular stack of squares like
this one here where there's one square
in the first row all the way down to M
squares in the bottom
row let's start with a triangular stack
of squares corresponding to the
Triangular number T subn that means
there's n blocks in the bottom row in
the first row place one token so we'
placed T1 tokens in the second row Place
one token in the first square and two
tokens in the second Square so that
we've placed T2 tokens in the second row
then Place T3 tokens in the third row as
1 + 2 + 3 continue this pattern in each
row placing I tokens in the I Square in
the row then the number of tokens in
this triangular diagram is given by the
sum of the first n triangular numbers T1
plus T2 and so on up to TN to find this
sum we perform a trick we create two two
more triangular arrays like this in the
first one we place the same number of
tokens in each row but this time we
place the tokens in reverse order
starting with the largest number of
tokens in a row and going down to one in
the third triangular array we place the
same number of tokens but this time we
go column by column starting from the
end so the last column has one token the
second from the last column has T2
tokens and so on so that the First
Column has TN tokens so the total number
of tokens spread across these three
three triangular arrays is 3 * the sum
of the first n triangular numbers now we
perform the trick stack all three of
these triangular arrays together
aggregating the number of tokens at any
spot it turns out that in any single
spot we always have exactly n plus 2
tokens on that spot and therefore 3 *
the sum of the first n triangular
numbers must be equal to n + 2times the
number of squares in the Triangular
array which is T subn and that
simplifies to n * n + 1 over2 so we used
three stacks of triangular arrays with a
triangular number of tokens in each row
to see that the sum of the first n
triangular numbers is n * n + 1 * n + 2
all divided 6 in his first proof without
words compendium Roger Nelson attributes
this proof to Richard K guy can you see
other identities you can prove using
stacks of tokens on certain arrays check
the linked video where we show how to
use this technique to find the sum of
the first n squares